Finding Aid for the Lloyd E. Cotsen Cuneiform Tablets Collection LSC.1883
UCLA Library Special Collections
- School text, cylinder seal exercise., Old Babylonian - Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); PARS 133; Obverse 1. Princess, 2. Daughter of Zali; 1 13/16" H x 1 1/4" W x 1/2" depth, sealed rectangular single column tablet; Rectangular tablet of grey-tan clay. There are significant losses to at one corner. There are mineral deposits on the surface of this loss, possibly salts (?) On this same face, there are two deep grooves that were created with an implement. It is possible these were made while the clay was still wet. Alternatively, these could have been made with a modern tool. There are some incomplete cracks, other minor surface losses, a nd a few white concretions overall. The raised portions of the surface have a slight sheen -- this sheen is possibly the result of handling and wear or from a coating. (Drawer 6)
  This tablet contains a student's practice rolling a cylinder seal onto the tablet face. The sealing reads, "Rubatum ('Princess'), daugher of Zali". Most administrative and legal documents required sealings.
- School text, lexical exercise., Ur III Period (c. 2100-2000 BCE); 31719.7; 1. … 2. … 3. A beard; 4. A wool beard; 2 5/8" diameter x 3/4" depth, lentil with an adhesive label attached; This lenticular tablet has some incomplete cracks throughout. There is a gouge mark that runs from one of the edges to the surface of the uninscribed face. This mark was made with a modern tool. There is a minor loss at part of the edge on the inscribed face as well as some minor spalling. There are other minor surface losses overall. There are white concretions visible overall. There is a small cream-colored label with a typed number "7" adhered to the uninscribed face.
- School text, letter exercise., Old Babylonian Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); SC-I-19; 2 3/4" height x 1 3/4" width x 11/16" depth, baked rectangular single column tablet joined from fragments; Rectangular tablet of red-brown clay that has been broken into three pieces. The pieces have been reattached with an adhesive. There is a gash-like loss near one edge on the inscribed face and another minor surface loss near another edge. There is a rectangular loss on the surface of the uninscribed face close to the center of the tablet. There is another loss on one edge and some minor chipping near two of the corners. (Drawer 2)
  This practice letter written by a student concerns quantities of barley exchanged between Ahum and Sin-nada.
- School text, lexical exercise from Ura 1., Old Babylonian Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); SC-IV-1B; Obverse (All but last line effaced) 13. Equid's nose rope Reverse 1. Throne 2. … 3. … 4. Raft 5. … 6. Nails 7. A type of plow 8. 9. … 10. … chariot 11. Poplar … 12. Popular … 13. Poplar seed; 2 3/4" height x 1 15/16" width x 1" depth, rectangular single column tablet; Rectangular tablet with losses at two corners. There is one small chip that may possibly have been reattached with an adhesive (?). There is an area on one face that has been scraped with a modern tool. There are incomplete cracks overall, particularly around the losses. There are white concretions visible overall. (Drawer 3)
- School text, mathematical exercise., Old Babylonian Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); SC-III-7; (Too damaged to reconstruct); 2 15/16" height x 2 3/4" width x 13/16" depth, square tablet with the surfaces effaced; A flat-faced, square tablet. The surface has considerable wear which obscures the rather large cuneiform symbols. There appear to be post-depositional layers of clay or soil on one face that have been partially scraped away. The tablet is actively crumbling and there are small detached fragments in its poly bag.
  This student practice is well-used and erased. It was likely used a "scrap paper" by students.
- School text, mathematical exercise., Old Babylonian - Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); 96501; 3 3/16" height x 1 13/16" width x 7/8" depth, rectangular single column tablet; Rectangular tablet that is actively crumbling. There are some surface losses overall, including some losses at three of the corners. There are modern tool marks at one corner as well as across one edge. There are some incomplete cracks overall. One particulalry long crack that runs across most of one edge is covered with a clear adhesive. There is another spot covered with clear adhesive on one face enar a corner, however, there does not seem to be a crack in this area. There are some white concretions visible overall. (Drawer 5)
  This text is a student practice problem for equivalencies between units of length.
- School text, literary exercise., Old Babylonian Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); 94; 2 11/16" height x 2" width x 7/8" depth, fragment; Cuneiform tablet fragment with uneven breaks and losses around all edges. One long side of the fragment has deep cracks that may need to be stabilized. One face has a small but deep hole near one edge. The tablet has a large and deep loss below that hole- part of the fragment that remains intact in that area may be the remains of an envelop. The opposite face has areas of spallng at both short edges and a small area of spalling at one long edge. A white circular sticker with "94." written in ink was affixed to one broken short side; the sticker has been removed. (Drawer 6)
- School text, lexical exercise., Ur III Period (c. 2100-2000 BCE); 31719.11; 1. unknown type of reed 2. unknown type of reed; 2 1/2" diameter x 13/16" depth, lentil with an adhesive label attached; This lenticular tablet has some incomplete cracks on the uninscribed face. There are some very minor losses to the surface of the uninscribed face. There are some small, white concretions visible on the surface overall. There is a small, cream-colored label with a typed "11" adhered to the uninscribed face near the edge. (Drawer 1)
- School text, administrative exercise of rations for weavers., Old Babylonian Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); SC-III-28c; 4 3/8" height x 1 7/8" width x 5/8" depth, rectangular single column tablet; Rectangular tablet of grey-brown clay. There are several incomplete cracks on the flat face of this tablet. A portion of one of these cracks appears to have had an adhesive or coating applied to it. There are losses on two corners. Both corners with these losses have adhesive applied on the surface. There is a loss on a portion of an edge next to one of these corners that has been reattached with an adhesive. It seems like portions of the break have been filled. The surface in this area is uneven and any previously existing script is unreadable. There are some minor losses to the surface, particularly on the flat face. There is one edge that has three blackened spots marking the surface. Another edge has two similarly sized spots, though not blackened, the outlines of which look to be shallowly incised. It is unclear what these markings are. There are white concretions visible throughout, particularly on the flat face. (Drawer 2)
- School text, lexical exercise of personal names., Old Babylonian Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); SC-III-34b; 5 1/4" height x 3 3/4" width x 1 1/16" depth, baked rectangular single column tablet with an adhesive label and ink mark"BF 22 'B'"; Rectangular tablet that has broken into two pieces. The two pieces have been reattached with a clear adhesive. Dried adhesive is visible on the surface along the break. There are surface losses along the edges and three of the corners. There is some spalling in these areas. There are some areas of the surface that have a white sheen where it looks like discoloration of the clay has occurred but it is possible that some sort of coating has been applied or built up in these. There is a white label adhered to one edge inscribed with: C. 3. This label appears to be partially covering more script reading: 2'B'. This script is written directly on the surface of the tablet in black ink or paint. It is possible there is more of this script completely covered by the white label. (Drawer 3)
- School text, lexical exercise of personal names beginning with "en"., Old Babylonian - Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); PARS 109; 1. 'The lord pouring forth luxuriance'; 2. 'The destructive lord of Inanna'; 3. 'The lord of the shrine'; 4. 'The lord of the beloved ritual cleansing'; 5. From the outside to the inside.; 3 3/4" diameter x 3/4" depth, lentil joined from fragments with the reverse inscribed; Lenticular tablet fragment reconstructed from at least three (but possibly much more than three) smaller fragments that were reattached. Approximately 1/4 of the tablet is lost. All the remaining fragments are held together with clear adhesive; there are still wide complete cracks, and adhesive is visible within several of them. One face has a large gouge toward center; this gouge borders the crack created by one of the reattached breaks. That crack runs to the edge of the tablet. Just above the crack at this edge there is a large, wedge-shaped loss. Part of the tablet adjacent to that loss has spalled. About one inch over from the wedge-shaped loss is a second loss; this one is at the edge of another reattached break. Near the edge furthest from the large missing portion of the tablet, there are three shallow gouges, a notched loss, and a deep gouge. Several cracks of varying depths are all over this face. The opposite face shows less damage. There is a deep gouge at one edge- to one side of that is a wedge-shaped loss. Closer toward center of the tablet are two shallower gouges. Deep cracks are visible on this face, but not as many as are visible on the other face. Some spots of adhesive are visible on the surface. The tablet may be lightly coated with an unknown substance. (Drawer 4)
- School text, letter exercise., Old Babylonian Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); PARS 41; 4 7/8" height x 2 5/8" width x 7/8" depth, red rectangular single column tablet joined from fragments; The tablet has been broken into multiple pieces and reassembled using an unidentified, clear adhesive. Numerous fragments ranging in size from 2.75 cm to powder are present in the poly bag. These appear to be recent damage (occured after the repairs done with the clear adhesive). The tablet also has three conically-shaped surface losses on one face. The tablet is actively crumbling. (Drawer 5)
  This student exercise is practice in drafting a letter using the appropriate format and techniques. The text is dated, "The year after Ami-ditana became king" (c. 1683).
- School text, lexical exercise of bronze objects., Old Babylonian - Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); PARS 144; 1. A double edged bronze ax 2. A bronze cauldron 3. A perforated bronze cauldron 4. A bronze lance 5. A bronze dagger 6. A bronze statue 7. A bronze pedestal 8. A bronze (statue) of a protective deity; 4 1/8" height x 4" width x 1 1/8" depth, red baked square double column tablet with the second column erased; Tablet is fragmentary; a large section is broken evenly and lost from one end. There is a loss to one corner. A web of deep, but not complete, cracks radiated out from the lost corner. There are deep but incomplete cracks on the reverse side which has no cuneiform impressions. There is no evidence of adhesive; the surface may be coated or the object is well fired. Possible tool mark (from excavation ?) in broken edge. Other horizontal toolmarks on uninscribed face are probably the result of a wood stylus (in antiquity). (Drawer 6)
  This elementary student exercise is practice writing basic vocabulary for metal objects. This text is not part of a known vocabulary list.
- School text, sign exercise from Syllable Alphabet A., Old Babylonian Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); SC-I-1; (Syllabary--no translation); 2 15/16" height x 1 15/16" width x 7/8" depth, rectangular single column tablet; Rectangular tablet of grey-brown clay. The tablet has uneven edges, this is possibly due to the original shape of the tablet and some losses. One of the corners is diagonal. It is difficult to gauge whether or not this is the result of the clay being pressed in while wet or if it is from a later loss. One end of the tablet is narrower than the other in width. It seems likely that this was the original shape of the tablet and not a result of losses from damage. One of the faces has losses to the surface as well as some white concretions. The other face has a small, round gouge, although it is not clear what caused this damage. There are also a few cracks on the edges. (Drawer 1)
  This beginner's exercise is a practice in sign formation and sound. Notice that the tablet turns left-to-right not top-to-bottom, as is customary.
- School text, mathematical exercise of surveying., Old Babylonian Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); SC-III-27; 3 7/8" height x 2 7/16" width x 1 1/16" depth, rectangular single column tablet joined from fragments; Rectangular tablet that has broken into two pieces. The pieces have been reattached with an adhesive. This adhesive has also been applied to the surface around the break. There are some losses along the break creating gaps and crevices between the two pieces. On one face, there are four groove marks near one side that seem to have been made by a modern implement. There is another groove mark on one edge. There are other minor surface losses and a few spots of adhesive overall. There are white concretions throughout, particularly on the convex face. (Drawer 2)
  This basic student exercise contains the measurements for several fields.
- School text, mathematical exercise., Old Babylonian Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); SC-I-35; 4 5/8" height x 3" width x 1 3/8" depth, rectangular tablet; Rectangular tablet that has broken into two pieces. These pieces have been reattached with an adhesive. There are losses on one corner and on the edge near this corner. There is a complete crack running parallel to the break. There is another complete crack running over an edge that turns into an incomplete crack running across one face. On this same face, there is a small pit-like loss with a black substance partially filling it. There is also a surface loss near one corner edge. On the other face, there is a shallow, grooved ditch measuring about 1 1/2" long running through the center of the tablet that possibly was made when the clay was still wet. There are white concretions visible on the surface throughout. (Drawer 3)
  This student exercise is a word problem accompanied by diagrams of triangles to help solve the problem.
- School text., Old Babylonian Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); SC-II-12; 3 3/8" height x 2 7/8" width x 7/8" depth, rectangular tablet; Ovoid tablet partially inscribed on one face. The partially inscribed face has two areas of spalling diagonally across from each other, revealing lighter colored clay than the rest of the tablet. One of these areas has a white crystalline spot on it that may be salt. At one edge there is a gouge, but this damage is old, as it has the same patina as the rest of the tablet. The uninscribed face has a large gouge or area of spalling on one edge. Another edge has an uneven loss. White crystalline spots are scattered on this face, mostly within damaged areas. (Drawer 4)
  This student practice was made from a recycled lexical list of personal names.
- School text, sign exercise from Syllable Alphabet A., Old Babylonian Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); PARS 98; (Syllabary--no translation); 5 1/2" height x 3" width x 1 5/8" depth, red hexagonal prism fragment joined from fragments; The fragment is half of a hexagonal-shaped tablet that was split approximately down the middle. A deep crack runs almost the full height of the exterior along one corner, stopping about one inch from the undamaged end. This crack has been repaired with a clear adhesive. There are other incomplete vertical hairline cracks on the incised faces. This fragment has a broken piece detached from one of its ends. This break and the interior surface are rough and uneven. The interior has a green/dark gray patina over much of the surface. A small amount of this residue is on the lower portion of the exterior, near the flat end. A shiny material is visible in some cracks; this is possibly adhesive or some other substance used to coat the fragment. (Drawer 5)
  This beginner's exercise is a practice in sign formation and sound. When complete, this prism contained the entire 124 line composition.
- School text, lexical exercise of personal names beginning with "Nanna" and Proto-An = Anum., Old Babylonian - Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); PARS 82; 4 5/8" height x 3" width x 1 1/8" depth, red baked rectangular tablet joined from fragments; Rectangular tablet fragment with a large portion lost so that two of the edges are quite uneven. The fragment has broken into eight pieces. These pieces have been reattached with an adhesive. The clear adhesive is visible along portions of the breaks. Two of the pieces are actually roughly a portion of the tablet that has split in half depth-wise. A few of the other pieces are much smaller than others. There are losses along the breaks creating jagged edges and crevices. There is an area near one of the edges on the convex face that is spalling. There are incomplete cracks and other minor surface losses overall. A coating has been applied to the surface of the fragment. (Drawer 6)
  This basic student exercise is practice writing personal names beginning with the deity name "Nanna". The reverse is a selection from the Old Babylonian word list Proto-An = Anum.
- School text, lexical exercise of words beginning with "ki"., Old Babylonian Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); SC-I-4; 1. A true place. 2. The stone was found.; 2 5/8" height x 2 3/8" width x 1 1/8" depth, baked square single column tablet; Square-shaped tablet with one corner pressed in, most likely when the clay was still wet. There are a few losses on the inscribed face near the edges and one circular loss along one edge. The uninscribed face has an uneven surface- there are some grooves and ditches where it looks like the clay was pressed or pinched when wet during the molding process. On this same side, there is also a small, circular gouge on the surface, possibly made by an implement. While the patina is quite dark overall, there are notably some black spots on one edge. (Drawer 1)
  This basic student exercise lists vocabulary that begin with "ki". This type of acrographic grouping was popular in ancient Mesopotamian practice vocabularies.
- School text, lexical exercise from Ura 1., Old Babylonian Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); SC-I-23; 2 13/16" height x 1 7/8" width x 15/16" depth, rectangular single column tablet; Rectangular tablet of grey-brown clay. There is one small, incomplete crack on one side near one edge. There are a few small creases and shallow scratches in the clay, most likely made when the clay was wet. There are some small, white concretions overall. (Drawer 2)
- School text, mathematical exercise of reciprocals., Old Babylonian Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); SC-I-32; 2 5/8" height x 1 11/16" width x 1/2" depth, rectangular single column tablet; Rectangular tablet fragment of grey-tan clay with losses at two edges and two corners. Approximately a quarter of the surface of one side is missing. There are some minor losses on the surface of the tablet overall. Some spalling is especially visible on the uninscribed face and there a few incomplete cracks on one edge. (Drawer 3)
  This tablet contains a student's exercise in reciprocals.
- Letter from king Rim-Suen of Larsa., Old Babylonian Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); SC-III-3; 3 7/8" height x 1 15/16" width x 7/8" depth, baked rectangular tablet with the reverse uninscribed; Rectangular tablet with one partially-inscribed face and one uninscribed face. The partially-inscribed face has spalling at the uninscribed edge. Several deep cracks run through the uninscribed portion, continuing onto the inscribed portion or onto the side. One corner of the inscribed portion has a small gouged loss. The uninscribed face has a gouge near one corner that extends onto the short side. A deep, complete crack runs down the face, across the gouge, and over onto the other face. The corner closest to that damaged corner has a large area of spalling. There are several cracks on the short side affected by the gouge/crack. The clay of this tablet is milky light tan in color. (Drawer 4)
  This royal letter is from king Rim-Suen concerning agricultural and irrigation matters. Rim-Suen reigned from 1822-1763 BCE.
- School text, lexical exercise from OB Nippur Lu., Old Babylonian Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); SC-III-13; 1. To tighten the strings 2. To slacked the strings 3. Fastened strings 4. To tune up 5. To tune down 6. Part of an instrument? 7. To tune 8. The fret 9. A musician 10. A chief musician 11. A string player 12. A musician in the service of the suhurla women 13. A royal musician 14. An apprentice musician 15. A … musician 16. A musician of a shrine 17. A musician of a divine shrine 18. A musician with a loud voice; 5" height x 2 5/8" width x 11/16" depth, rectangular single column tablet joined from fragments; This rectangular tablet is actively crumbling; there are loose particles of clay in the storage bag. The tablet is inscribed on one face only. It was broken into two pieces that were reattached using clear adhesive. On the inscribed face, lines of adhesive are on the surface of the face at the reattached break, at an incomplete diagonal crack extending from the break, and at a break that runs from about the center of the face out to the edge. Adhesive has also bled along some of the inscribed lines on the face. One corner of the face has an approximately- square loss. A thin crack extending from this loss has adhesive covering it. The corner opposite the square loss has a larger diagonal loss. A third corner is spalled. There is a gouged loss at one edge of the tablet that adjoins the crack filled with adhesive (described above). The uninscribed face is very fragile with a dry, flaking texture overall. The clay particles in the bag almost certainly flaked from this face. The repaired break in the tablet is visible on this face, and adhesive is present on the surface. The short end of this face closest to the repaired reak has losses to both corners, gouges, and flaking. There is a small loss to a third corner. There is a goughed loss at one edge (also visible on the inscribed face). There are tiny flaking cracks scattered throughout this face. (Drawer 5)
- School text, literary exercise from a hymn to Inanna., Old Babylonian - Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); PARS 123; 4 1/2" diameter x 11/16" depth, baked multi-column lentil joined from fragments; A lenticular tablet that has broken into numerous pieces and been reassembled. The fragments have been attached with an unidentified, clear adhesive. One small fragment has recently detached and is in the poly bag. This appears to be lost through spalling due to salt crystals. The area with the loss has a build up of a white concretion material, probably salt. There is a long gouge running vertically down the convex face that appears to have been made when the clay was wet. The convex face has multiple hairline cracks. (Drawer 6)
  This advanced student exercise is a literary excerpt from a hymn to the goddess Inanna. The second column is blank. This format is an unusual exercise and layout.
- School text, legal exercise of a lawsuit., Old Babylonian Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); SC-III-23a; 4 5/8" height x 2 1/16" width x 1" depth, rectangular single column tablet; Rectangular tablet made of dark brown (almost black) clay. On one face, the corner has a scrape that appears to be caused by a modern tool- the clay here is lighter in color than the rest of the tablet. There is a small, chipped loss at one corner. The opposite face has a small chip or gouge near center. This damage is ancient, as it has the same patina as the rest of the tablet. (Drawer 1)